Guide to the Elizabeth and Felix G. Rohatyn Papers Circa 1900?-2020 (bulk 1975-2012) MS 3015
New-York Historical Society
Elizabeth and Felix G. Rohatyn papers
circa 1900?-2020 (bulk 1975-2012)
New-York Historical Society
Rohatyn, Felix G., 1928-2019
MS 3015
14.75 Linear feet in 17 boxes of various sizes
The Elizabeth and Felix G. Rohatyn papers include documents related to the Rohatyns's public service, philanthropy, and policy advocacy on matters of infrastructure investment, political economy and international relations, especially for the 1990s and early 2000s. Felix's speeches, writings and interviews on these subjects are found throughout the collection. Felix's years as ambassador to France (1997-2000) are represented in the collection. Elizabeth's work on the Boards of the not-for-profits French Regional & American Museum Exchange (FRAME) and Teaching Matters, Inc. (TMI) are included, with some files concerning the New York Public Library. The collection includes many personal photographs of the Rohatyns and their family.
Arrangement Note
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series I. General Correspondence and Subject Files, 1982-2016 (bulk, 2001-2010)
Series II. New York City Fiscal Crisis, 1975-2013
Series III. Remarks, Speeches and Writings, 1980s-2016
Series IV. Ambassadorship Files, 1994-2001 (bulk, 1997-2000)
Series V. Elizabeth Rohatyn Board Files, 1993-2013
Series VI. Personal Photographs and Biographical Documents, Circa 1900?-2017
Biographical/Historical Note
Felix George Rohatyn was born on 29 May 1928 in Vienna, Austria. His family moved to France in 1935 where his parents divorced and his mother remarried. Rohatyn and his mother (Edith Plessner) and his step-father (Henry Plessner), all Jews, narrowly escaped Nazi-occupied France in 1940. With the intervention of Luiz Martins de Souza Dantas, the Brazilian ambassador to France, the family eventually moved to Brazil. In June 1942, the family arrived in New York City. Beginning in 1944, Rohatyn attended Middlebury College in Vermont. He returned to France briefly in 1947 to reunite with his father at his brewing business, but then returned to America to graduate in 1949 from Middlebury with a degree in physics. Rohatyn's stepfather's acquaintance with André Meyer, the head of the investment banking firm Lazard Frères, led to Felix joining the firm in 1949, setting the course of his professional life in finance.
Rohatyn became a U.S. citizen in May 1950. His initial assignments for Lazard had him working for affiliated firms in Europe, but these were interrupted when Rohatyn was drafted into the U.S. Army from 1951 to 1953. He went through basic training at Camp Atterbury, Indiana, and the Army Intelligence School at Fort Riley, Kansas. Assigned to the 28th Infantry Division, Rohatyn was sent to Germany at the rank of sergeant and with the title of Order of Battle Specialist. At the conclusion of his military service, he returned to Lazard, working first in Europe and then joining the New York office in 1955, where he would remain until 1997. In 1956, Rohatyn married Jeannette Streit, an interpreter who worked on the United Nations staff. They would have three sons together: Pierre, Nicolas and Michael.
By the early 1960s, Rohatyn was a partner at Lazard, working as an investment banker with mergers and acquisitions. The nature of this work led him beyond Lazard, taking positions on the Boards of firms he advised, such as ITT, and positions supporting the financial industry more generally, such as being on the New York Stock Exchange's Board of Governors (1968-72). This expanding network eventually led, in 1975, to Rohatyn being asked by New York Governor Hugh Carey to bring his expertise to bear on the fiscal crisis faced by New York City. As part of the rescue initiative, a new entity, the Municipal Assistance Corporation (MAC) was formed, and Rohatyn was named its Chairman within a few months of its creation. Rohatyn helped lead the effort to manage New York's brush with bankruptcy through 1975 and then through the following years as the city's finances stabilized and strengthened. Rohatyn stayed on with MAC until 1993 when he stepped down as Chairman.
In 1979, Rohatyn married his second wife, Elizabeth (née Fly). Elizabeth was born in 1930 in Memphis. She had been previously married twice and had a daughter, Nina, from her first marriage. Through the 1980s, the Rohatyns expanded their philanthropic activities, including support for the I Have a Dream Foundation (the 1986 cohort of students in the program is known as the "Rohatyn cohort") and with Elizabeth joining the Board of Trustees of the New York Public Library in 1985. In 1994, Elizabeth founded Teaching Matters Inc. (TMI), a not-for-profit organization aimed at enhancing the effectiveness of teachers and school administrators, especially with respect to the integration of technology into schools.
In April 1997, Felix resigned from Lazard and a few months later was named by President Bill Clinton to the position of Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary of the United States of America to France. He and Elizabeth moved to Paris where they served until December 2000. Near the conclusion of Rohatyn's tenure as ambassador, Elizabeth founded a new organization, the French Regional & American Museum Exchange (FRAME). The mission of the organization was, and is, to develop U.S.-France cultural exchanges in the context of museum collaborations for exhibitions, education programs, and the like. Elizabeth served as Co-Founding Co-President of FRAME, along with Francoise Cachin, who was then the Director of the Musées de France.
Returning to America in 2001, Felix formed an advisory firm, Rohatyn Associates LLC, and also served on the Boards of various business interests and policy groups, such as the Center for Strategic & International Studies (CSIS). During the early 2000s, he more fully developed as an advocate for government investment in America's infrastructure, a theme he elaborated in his book Bold Endeavors: How Our Government Built America, and Why It Must Rebuild Now (2009). He also wrote a memoir, Dealings: A Political and Financial Life (2010), of his career in finance, reflecting on his early career, his work in mergers and acquisitions for Lazard, and New York City's crisis year of 1975. He returned to Lazard in 2010 as an adviser to Chairman and Chief Executive Kenneth M. Jacobs. Rohatyn died on December 14, 2019.
Elizabeth had been named Chairman of the New York Public Library in November 1995, and returned to America in 2001 to continue her active involvement on the Board as Chairman Emeritus. She also continued her active engagement with Teaching Matters, FRAME, and other organizations. Elizabeth died in 2016.
(The above note was based on various sources including, among others, Felix Rohatyn's memoir Dealings; the Wikipedia entry for Rohatyn; the websites for FRAME and for Teaching Matters; the New York Times obituary for Elizabeth; and documents in the collection.)
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The collection was donated by Felix G. Rohatyn in May 2015. A small amount of additional material was donated in December 2017.
Scope and Contents Note
The Elizabeth and Felix G. Rohatyn papers include documents related to the Rohatyns's public service, philanthropy, and policy advocacy on matters of political economy and international relations, especially for the 1990s and early 2000s. The collection includes an extensive set of Felix's correspondence files from the 2000s that principally concern his advocacy for government investment in national infrastructure projects, along with political and business matters. These files hold correspondence from many notable individuals, including U.S. presidents (especially Bill Clinton), many U.S. senators and congressmen and congresswomen, business leaders, and others. Rohatyn's policy advocacy is documented in his speeches, articles and other writings, and interviews found throughout the collection. There is a set of papers from Rohatyn's years as ambassador to France (1997-2000), including confirmation documents, schedules, and binders of the speeches he made during these years. Rohatyn's activities with respect to New York City's fiscal crisis in 1975 are lightly represented with clippings and a series of photographic negatives taken in connection with activities of the Municipal Assistance Corporation and legislation signed by President Jimmy Carter in August 1978.
Elizabeth Rohatyn's initiatives in the educational and cultural arenas are well-represented in the collection. Elizabeth's founding of and continuing engagement with the French Regional & American Museum Exchange (FRAME) and with Teaching Matters, Inc. (TMI) are included, as are some files concerning her involvement with the Board of Trustees of the New York Public Library. Elizabeth's involvement in social diplomacy as the wife of the ambassador to France is reflected in the collection.
The collection also holds many photographs of Felix, Elizabeth and their families. Felix's years as a child, as a young man, in the military, in leisure activities like skiing, with Bill Clinton, at award ceremonies, and others are in the collection. One photograph of Felix was taken and autographed by Richard Avedon. Elizabeth is represented in photographs primarily from later years with Felix and at gala events, likely associated with the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
Ambassadors.; Government spending policy; Black-and-white negatives; Clippings (information artifacts); Letters (correspondence); Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Clinton, Bill, 1946- -- Correspondence; Rohatyn, Elizabeth F., 1930-2016; Rohatyn, Felix G., 1928-2019; French American Museum Exchange; Municipal Assistance Corporation for the City of New York; New York Public Library; Teaching Matters Inc
- Series I. General Correspondence and Subject Files, 1982-2016 (bulk, 2001-2010); 4.11 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents Note
  The series includes files of Felix Rohatyn's correspondence, primarily from 2001 to about 2010, that is, the years after his ambassadorship to France. A significant theme running through much, perhaps most, of the correspondence is Rohatyn's advocacy for government investment in national infrastructure projects. This theme emerges in various contexts, notably in files concerning the transition team for New York Governor-elect Eliot Spitzer (2006), for a meeting of state investment officials convened by Rohatyn, California State Treasurer Philip Angelides and New York Comptroller H. Carl McCall regarding potential use of pension plans for infrastructure development (2002), long-term planning for New York under Mayor Michael Bloomberg (2002), rebuilding in New York after the attacks of 9/11 on the World Trade Center (2001), and the National Governors Association consideration of federal spending on building (2009). The files include remarks and articles by Rohatyn on the subject, with contextual documents such as clippings, government reports, and other material. (Standalone files of Rohatyn's writings and remarks are found in other series.) The World Trade Center attacks themselves also emerge as a subject, as correspondents from both the U.S. and overseas write to Rohatyn expressing sympathy for the tragic events of 9/11.
  Rohatyn's advisory business interests are another theme of the series, though these appear in less depth. The series holds some early financial statements and required firm policy documents for Rohatyn's advisory firm, Rohatyn Associates LLC; a company overview of Lazard (2009); and a few Board meeting packets for companies at which Rohatyn served as a Board member. The economic relationship between the U.S. and Europe, Rohatyn's philanthropy, his support for certain politicians and public policy objectives, opposition to the death penalty, and awards and other recognitions bestowed on Rohatyn are among the other topics of the correspondence.
  The correspondents found in the series are principally from the worlds of finance/business and politics. There are several letters from President Bill Clinton, with Presidents Richard Nixon, George H.W. Bush, and George W. Bush also appearing. Letters from Supreme Court Justices, Cabinet officials, senators, and congressmen and congresswomen are also found in the series, as are letters from New York City mayors, corporate executives, and international statesmen and businesspeople. Nonetheless, many of these letters are not especially substantive, often simply expressing thanks or other courtesy on a matter. Overall, the container list identifies at the folder level any notable individuals, particularly from the political arena, and subjects. Many of the letters to and from overseas correspondents are in French.
  The series also includes several folders of general press clippings and tear sheets concerning business, economics, and other such matters, several of which refer to Rohatyn.
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged in alphabetical order, which is principally by correspondent but also includes subject matter references. This follows the original order of a set of files, into which loose and unlabeled documents were added by the processing archivist. Most loose documents were added into the original "miscellaneous" folders, which already held most of the correspondence. Folder labels created by the archivist for certain correspondents and subjects that were not in the original set are not differentiated in the container list below, but are shown in [brackets] on the actual boxed folders. Miscellaneous news articles and other reference material are at the end of the files.
  - American Embassy in Paris, 2001-2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Academie des Sciences Morales et Politiques (2 folders), 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2-3)
    Includes notes and other preparatory material for a speeech at the Academie, but not the speech itself. The file includes Rohatyn's related speech given at the New York Public Library in April 2001, "A New Europe, A New America: Drifting Apart at the Turn of the Century."
  - Address [Contact] Lists (7 folders) (Restricted until 2030), circa 2000-2009 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1-7)
  - Adler, Michael, 2001-2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Albright, Madeleine, 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Altman, Roger C., 2002-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes letter co-signed by Rohatyn in connection with his support of a fundraising event for presidential candidate John Kerry.
  - American Academy of Arts & Sciences, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    General Note
    Includes draft of Rohatyn's essay "The Financial Scandals and the Demise of the Traditional Investment Banker."
  - American Hospital of Paris Foundation, 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Jewish Committee; Amerian Jewish Historical Society, 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    Includes the invitation for the event honoring Rohatyn with the Emma Lazarus Statue of Liberty Award.
  - American Society of the French Legion of Honor, 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes roster of members.
  - Anti-Defamation League (ADL), 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Apple, Betsey, 2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Condolences and response on the death of R.W. Apple.
  - Appointment Books (5), 2007-2008, 2013-2015 (Offsite-box 16, Item 1-5)
  - Aspen Strategy Group; Aspen Institute Italia, 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    Includes Rohatyn's paper on the "New Europeans" and a copy of his Washington Post piece "On the Wrong Track."
  - AXA, 2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    Includes material related to the International Commission on Holocaust Era Insurance Claims (ICHEIC).
  - A. Miscellaneous, 2000-2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
    Includes, among other correspondents, District Attorney Lynne Abraham expressing gratitude for Rohatyn's help in obtaining the extradition of a criminal from France.
  - Barrett, Bill, 2001-2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bloomberg, Michael (Mayor), 2002-2007 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
    Includes, among other material, a presentation of the Mayor's Office of Long-Term Planning and Sustainability's "PlaNYC 2030: Transforming New York's Urban Environment" and Rohatyn's comments on the plan published on FT.com (2007).
  - Brookings Institution, 2001-2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes, among other material, Brookings's "A Compact Between the United States and Europe," supported by Rohatyn, a member of the Brookings Council.
  - Bush, George H.W.; Bush, George W., 1991,2001-2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
    Includes one G.H.W. Bush letter referring to his address at the Babi Yar Memorial in Kiev (1991) and one thank you letter from G.W. Bush (2001).
  - B. Miscellaneous (3 folders), 2000-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20-22)
    Includes letters from, among others, Trade Representative Charlene Barshefsky, former Senator Howard H. Baker, Jr., Fed Chairman Ben S. Bernanke, Samuel R. (Sandy) Berger (including forwarding two speeches by President Clinton on the new agenda of closing the international development gap), Senator Joseph R. Biden, Jr., Senator Christopher S. Bond, Supreme Court Justice Stephen Breyer, and Warren E. Buffett. Includes several French correspondents, including French Minister of the Economy, Finance, and Industry Thierry Breton, and two photographs of Pierre Betin when he was awarded the Legion of Honor.
  - Center for Strategic & International Studies (CSIS), 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
    Includes the report of CSIS's Embassy of the Future Commission, co-chaired by Rohatyn (2007).
  - Clinton, William Jefferson (Bill), 1987-2011 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 24)
    Includes one letter from Arkansas Governor Clinton (1987), seven letters from President Clinton (1995-1997), and three letters from Clinton, post-presidency (2002-2011). In an 8 June 1995 letter Clinton responds to Rohatyn's March 31 piece in the New York Times and comments on national budget and financial priorities. In a 22 April 1996 letter, Clinton comments on the late Secretary of Commerce Ron Brown. See also the ambassadorship series for two other Clinton letters related to Rohatyn's post.
  - Coface Speech, 2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 25)
    Includes Rohatyn's remarks at the Coface World Economic Forum "France, Europe and the U.S."
  - C. Miscellaneous (3 folders), 2001-2015 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 26-28)
    Includes, among others, letters from former Governor Mario Cuomo, Attorney General/Governor Andrew Cuomo, Senator Jon S. Corzine, Senator Thomas R. Carper, economist Bowman (Bo) Cutter, John D. Podesta of the Center for American Progress, Nancy J. Cooper of the American Consulate in Bordeaux (conveying Mayor Juppe's proposed projects for French-U.S. cooperation), and Lloyd N. Cutler (conveying draft of letter for Michel David-Weill of Lazard concerning the terms of Rohatyn's possible renewed relationship with the firm, now that his ambassadorship to France had ended).
  - Death Penalty / Roper v. Simmons (2 folders), 2001, 2005-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 29a-b)
    Includes documents related to Rohatyn's 2001 and 2006 articles concerning his opposition to the death penalty and his participation in the amicus briefs for McCarver v. North Carolina and for Simmons v. Roper. Includes a letter from Supreme Court Justice Anthony M. Kennedy (2005).
  - DeLauro, Rosa, 2007 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes a summary of the National Infrastructure Development Act (H.R. 3896), and the bill introduced by Congresswoman DeLauro.
  - Dinner Dance, May 12, 1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 31)
  - D. Miscellaneous, 1995, 2003, 2008-2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 32)
    Includes Senator Christopher Dodd confirming Rohatyn's participation at a Senate hearing on the nation's infrastructure (2008).
  - Economic Club of Chicago / Le Monde, 2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 33)
    Includes the speech for the Club, article for Le Monde, and associated reference documents, some of which are other Rohatyn's articles and speeches.
  - E. Miscellaneous, 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 34)
  - Financial Services Committee, 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 35)
    Includes draft of testimony before the congressional committee.
  - Foreign Investment, 2005-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 36)
  - Fundraising, 1986 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 37)
    Includes letters received in reaction to Rohatyn's article concerning fundraising events in New York, related magazine articles, and other letters related to the Rohatyns's philanthropy.
  - F. Miscellaneous, 2001, 2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 38)
  - Giscard d'Estaing, Valery, 2001-2004 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 39)
  - G. Miscellaneous (2 folders), 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 40-41)
    Includes, among others, Mayor Rudolph W. (Rudy) Giuliani and Congressman Richard A. (Dick) Gephardt.
  - HSBC, 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 42)
  - H. Miscellaneous, 1995-2016 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 43)
    Includes, among others, Senator Jesse Helms, Senator Chuck Hagel, and Congresswoman Jane Harman.
  - I Have A Dream, 1986, 1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes photocopies of junior high school student letters expressing their career dreams (1986) and a thank you letter to the Rohatyns from a "dreamer."
  - Infrastructure (2 folders), 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2-3)
    Includes the report "An Investment Strategy for Economic Recovery," a product of a meeting of state investment officials convened by Rohatyn, California State Treasurer Philip Angelides and New York Comptroller H. Carl McCall, with related documents (2001-2002); see also the folders below on "New York Rebuilding" and "Pension Funds." Includes Rohatyn-related clippings, interviews, etc. on the subject of infrastructure investment (2003-2010).
  - I. Miscellaneous, 2001-2010 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - John's Island Real Estate Company, Vero Beach, Florida, 2008 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes a packet of marketing material.
  - J. Miscellaneous, 1996, 2001-2004 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes, among others, literary agent Morton L. Janklow and a presentation concerning efforts for asbestos reform legislation.
  - Kerry, John, 1995, 2001-2004 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - Kissinger, Henry, 2001-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
  - K. Miscellaneous (2 folders), 2001-2008 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9-10)
    Includes, among others, New School University President Bob Kerrey, Senator Edward M. (Ted) Kennedy, Supreme Court Justice Anthony M. Kennedy, and former mayor Edward I. Koch. A letter from Koch includes substantive commentary on a 1 November 2003 speech made by Rohatyn.
  - Lazard (2 folders), 2009-2010 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11-12)
    Includes, among other documents, a "Company Overview" of Lazard (2009) and a packet for Rohatyn of schedules, briefing notes, and background documents for a May-June 2010 period.
  - L. Miscellaneous (3 folders), 1994, 2001-2007, 2016 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13-15)
    Includes, among others, Senators Patrick Leahy, Joseph I. Lieberman, Richard G. Lugar, and Maurice Levy (in French, concerning the Legion of Honor for Elizabeth Rohatyn).
  - Mahoney Cohen & Company, CPA, P.C., New York, NY, 2001 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
    Includes packet of marketing material.
  - Middlebury College Board of Trustees (2 folders), 2009 October (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17a-b)
  - Morris, W. Howard, 2012 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    Includes a copy of the Financial Stability Agreement between the city of Detroit and the Michigan Department of Treasury, in connection with a proposed conversation with Morris of the Detroit Financial Advisory Board.